Guide to the Stanford University, Euler Project, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Euler Project, records
1979-1988
SC0362
Stanford University. Euler Project.
Zapf, Hermann
2.25 Linear feet
Collection consists of Hermann Zapf's original drawings used to develop the Euler typeface, as well as computer printouts and proofs; correspondence between Zapf and Donald E. Knuth concerning the typeface design; and the working papers of the Digital Typography Group, which produced the final digital typeface, including correspondence, character proofs, galleys, computer programs, notebooks, logs, and research notes.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Hermann Zapf, 1988, and Donald E. Knuth, 1989.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Euler Project at Stanford produced a digital typeface, consisting of over 500 mathematical characters, for the American Mathematical Society (AMS). The typeface, named after the 18th century mathematician Leonhard Euler, was designed by German type designer Hermann Zapf. The typeface was produced using the METAFONT type design language, developed by Donald E. Knuth at Stanford University, and formulated by the Digital Typography Group at Stanford University.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists of Hermann Zapf's original drawings used to develop the Euler typeface, as well as computer printouts and proofs; correspondence between Zapf and Donald E. Knuth concerning the typeface design; and the working papers of the Digital Typography Group, which produced the final digital typeface, including correspondence, character proofs, galleys, computer programs, notebooks, logs, and research notes.
Access Terms
American Mathematical Society.; Kim, Scott.; Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-; Stanford University. Digital Typography Group.; Stanford University. Euler Project.; Zapf, Hermann; Computerized typesetting.; METAFONT (Computer system).
Collection Contents
- Zapf, Herman, Series 1
  - Correspondence: Donald Knuth to Hermann Zapf re: Euler Project, 1979 -1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Donald Knuth to Hermann Zapf re: Euler Project, 1981 -1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Euler: original drawings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Euler: sketches, notes, proofs, etc. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Euler: proofs and computer printouts (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Euler: computer printouts, July 30, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Euler: Fraktur computer printouts, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Euler: computer printouts, July 29, 1982 & August 2, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Euler: computer printouts, July 1, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Mathematical Society (AMS), letters & Symbols List (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Logo: Associates of Stanford University Libraries (includes correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Knuth, Donald, Series 2
  - Correspondence: Herman Zapf to Donald Knuth re: Euler Project, 8/20/79 -12/8/80 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Herman Zapf to Donald Knuth re: Euler Project, 9/16/80 -12/14/88 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Euler Digitization "The Euler Project At stanford" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Drawings of AMS Euler sent to stanford by Hermann Zapf (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Digital Typography Group, Series 3
  - Correspondence Ron to Dave, 09/10/--re: sizes for AMS -Euler (Ron is at the American Mathematical society or AMS) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Euler character proofs (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Character widths (in units) Nov. 1981 (Box 1)
  - Euler unscaled, bold galleys, 10 point, 7 point, 5 point photocopies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Euler character (Fraktur lowercase) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Program August 17, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Charles Bigelow, consultant, to Dave Siegel, February 18, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Evaluation of Metafont as Production Tool for AMS, March 1981, consultant report (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Galleys for various fonts, different points -10, 5, 7 -eurm, euf, ams euf, eusm (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Galley entitled A Paper received by AMS July 5, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Ron to Dave, Thur. 9/6, re: Euler update (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Euler proofs -Fraktur lowercase -Jan., Feb. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New Alphabets and Symbols for 'TYPesetting Mathematics, by Phoebe J. Murdock, AMS, c. 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Worksheets (photocopied) on Greek, Symbols, Fraktur (initialed by Zapf, 1983) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Proof of Fraktur capitals. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Handwritten Euler Greek bold on rom graph paper with data. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scott Kim Notebook: (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fraktur lowercase proofs (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 'Ihe principle for the metafont pens (init. by Zapf, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program Aug. 23, 1982 -EUFBAS.MF[EU.SEK] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program March 31, 1982 -EUFBAS.MF[EU.SEK] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 2/5/81 Knuth to Zapf (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 10/9/80 Knuth to Zapf (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scott Kim Notebook (cont'd): (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Euler Raman Proofs, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Metaface 101 -'Ihe Euler Project. An interactive interface for METAFONI'i Class project abstract (3 copies) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diagrams and flow charts (handwritten) for METAFONT (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "On the Graphic Design of Program Text" by A. Marcus and R. Baecker, May 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Program 2/27/83 -X. PSC[WRK.NWD] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photocopies of published material on letter development (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - OVerlays with notes and data (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Euler Raman control characters (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters on rom graph paper with notes and data (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photocopy of Albrecht Durer's Script, 1525 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Greek lowercase 3 control character (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Program 1/23/83 -FRAImJ.MF[FKM.DEM] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Metaface 101 -1 copy (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fraktur medium capitals for markup only (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Program 7/18/82 -FTEST.MF[EU,SEK] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Program 8/23/82 -SYMB.MF[l,BWW] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Program 8/23/82 -DRDl[EU,SEK] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Euler characters February 9,11,14, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Euler characters -1 sheet (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fraktur capitals worksheets (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Greek lowercase worksheets (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Euler script on rom graph paper with data (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fraktur character worksheets (init. by Zapf, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Roman character worksheets (init. by Zapf, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Italic character worksheets (init. by Zapf, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - OVeJ::View Euler Project (Oct, Dec 1982) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Font printout (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Euler Roman character corrections (init. by Zapf, 1983) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bitmaps of different scripts (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bitmap of Fraktur characters (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proof of Fraktur lowercase (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Proof of Fraktur capitals (init. by Zapf) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Hennann Zapf and Donald Knuth, re: 10/7/79 -5/17/84 (photocopies of originals) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Character worksheets (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Typographs by Frank Harary (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Character Reccx:mition Based on Phenomenolcx:rical Attributes, Blesser, et ale (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Alpha, omega and p proofs (OK by Zapf, 1983) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - AMS -Euler character worksheets with overlays (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fraktur characters worksheets (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Printout of Fraktur capital J;; with data points -12/13/82 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Trial of capital Fraktur -1/9/83 -(A -Z) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten characters on nun graph paper with data (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Digits, symbols and punctuation (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Greek character worksheets (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Numerals worksheet (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Printout of Greek alphabet (initialed by Zapf, 1981) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Euler project log (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Program to construct a working MEI'AFONT program with examples -Feb. 1981 -Donald Knuth (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Revised programs of 1981 with examples -sept. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Message to Donald Knuth from Scott Kim -12/21/81 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Message to Donald Knuth from Dan Mills and Carol Twombly summarizing their progress -11/18/82 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Iaserprinted Fraktur capitals by Carol Twombly and Dan Mills -Nov. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Euler Project 35nun color slides (8) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Galleys for various Fonts (Box 3, Folder 6)